<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Talks on Scott Jeen</title>
    <link>https://enjeeneer.io/talks/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Talks on Scott Jeen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&lt;a href=&#34;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;CC BY-NC 4.0&lt;/a&gt;</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 12 Nov 2024 14:18:07 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://enjeeneer.io/talks/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>4 Years in 4(ish) Minutes</title>
      <link>https://enjeeneer.io/talks/2024-11-12-phd-reflection/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Nov 2024 14:18:07 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://enjeeneer.io/talks/2024-11-12-phd-reflection/</guid>
      <description>[Click here for full-screen slideshow]</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dynamics Generalisation with Behaviour Foundation Models</title>
      <link>https://enjeeneer.io/talks/2024-08-09-rlc-tafm/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Aug 2024 17:01:15 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://enjeeneer.io/talks/2024-08-09-rlc-tafm/</guid>
      <description>[Click here for full-screen slideshow]</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The problem problem: choosing impactful research problems</title>
      <link>https://enjeeneer.io/talks/2024-06-14-reffciency/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Jun 2024 09:34:36 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://enjeeneer.io/talks/2024-06-14-reffciency/</guid>
      <description>[Click here for full-screen slideshow]
What are problems?  “A problem is a situation in which we experience conflicting ideas.”
David Deutsch
 Let’s start with a definition, here’s the best I’ve found for what constitutes a problem. David Deutsch says a problem is a situation in which we experience conflicting ideas. In other words we have two or more explanations about how we might proceed, and it&amp;rsquo;s not initially clear how to choose between them.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Zero Shot Building Control</title>
      <link>https://enjeeneer.io/talks/2022-06-23oxcav/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jun 2022 09:34:36 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://enjeeneer.io/talks/2022-06-23oxcav/</guid>
      <description>Abstract
Heating and cooling systems in buildings account for 31% of global energy use, much of which are regulated by Rule Based Controllers (RBCs) that neither maximise energy efficiency nor minimise emissions by interacting optimally with the grid. Control via Reinforcement Learning (RL) has been shown to significantly improve building energy efficiency, but existing solutions require pre-training in simulators that are prohibitively expensive to obtain for every building in the world.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Space Invasion, Space Invaders, and Climate Change Mitigation</title>
      <link>https://enjeeneer.io/talks/2021-06-03-jesusmcrgreen/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Jun 2021 11:50:52 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://enjeeneer.io/talks/2021-06-03-jesusmcrgreen/</guid>
      <description>Abstract
Recent advances in the field of Reinforcement Learning, a subfield of Artificial Intelligence, have shown computers can achieve superhuman performance at complex games like Go, Starcraft and the Atari Suite without human knowledge. What if, instead of playing Space Invaders, we play the game of climate change mitigation? More specifically, how can we design games where the goal is to minimise carbon emissions in some setting, and learn to play them optimally?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Taking a peek inside black-box function approximators</title>
      <link>https://enjeeneer.io/talks/2021-03-15-xchangeseminar/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Mar 2021 16:55:47 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://enjeeneer.io/talks/2021-03-15-xchangeseminar/</guid>
      <description>Abstract
In this talk, I will introduce deterministic and probabilistic black-box function approximators, with applications for timeseries modelling. First, I introduce the multilayer perceptron (neural network), demonstrating how they can model arbitrarily complex functions, but highlighting their propensity to overfit the training data. Second, I introduce the Gaussian process (GP), a bayesian, probabilistic approach to function approximation. I visualise how GP&amp;rsquo;s quantify uncertainty, a robust trait in the context of control, but highlight their inability to scale to large datasets.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
