<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Talks on Scott Jeen</title>
    <link>https://enjeeneer.io/talks/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Talks on Scott Jeen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&lt;a href=&#34;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;CC BY-NC 4.0&lt;/a&gt;</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 14 Jun 2024 09:34:36 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://enjeeneer.io/talks/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>The problem problem: choosing impactful research problems</title>
      <link>https://enjeeneer.io/talks/2024-06-14-reffciency/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Jun 2024 09:34:36 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://enjeeneer.io/talks/2024-06-14-reffciency/</guid>
      <description>[Click here for full-screen slideshow]
Agenda  What are problems? Identifying problems  Moral axioms, lemmas, and propositions Being the pareto best in the world   Checking the problem  Balancing feasiblility and usefulness Baselines and oracles   Takeaways  What are problems?  “A problem is a situation in which we experience conflicting ideas.”
David Deutsch
 Let’s start with a definition, here’s the best I’ve found for what constitutes a problem.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Zero Shot Building Control</title>
      <link>https://enjeeneer.io/talks/2022-06-23oxcav/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jun 2022 09:34:36 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://enjeeneer.io/talks/2022-06-23oxcav/</guid>
      <description>Abstract
Heating and cooling systems in buildings account for 31% of global energy use, much of which are regulated by Rule Based Controllers (RBCs) that neither maximise energy efficiency nor minimise emissions by interacting optimally with the grid. Control via Reinforcement Learning (RL) has been shown to significantly improve building energy efficiency, but existing solutions require pre-training in simulators that are prohibitively expensive to obtain for every building in the world.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Space Invasion, Space Invaders, and Climate Change Mitigation</title>
      <link>https://enjeeneer.io/talks/2021-06-03-jesusmcrgreen/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Jun 2021 11:50:52 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://enjeeneer.io/talks/2021-06-03-jesusmcrgreen/</guid>
      <description>Abstract
Recent advances in the field of Reinforcement Learning, a subfield of Artificial Intelligence, have shown computers can achieve superhuman performance at complex games like Go, Starcraft and the Atari Suite without human knowledge. What if, instead of playing Space Invaders, we play the game of climate change mitigation? More specifically, how can we design games where the goal is to minimise carbon emissions in some setting, and learn to play them optimally?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Taking a peek inside black-box function approximators</title>
      <link>https://enjeeneer.io/talks/2021-03-15-xchangeseminar/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Mar 2021 16:55:47 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://enjeeneer.io/talks/2021-03-15-xchangeseminar/</guid>
      <description>Abstract
In this talk, I will introduce deterministic and probabilistic black-box function approximators, with applications for timeseries modelling. First, I introduce the multilayer perceptron (neural network), demonstrating how they can model arbitrarily complex functions, but highlighting their propensity to overfit the training data. Second, I introduce the Gaussian process (GP), a bayesian, probabilistic approach to function approximation. I visualise how GP&amp;rsquo;s quantify uncertainty, a robust trait in the context of control, but highlight their inability to scale to large datasets.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://enjeeneer.io/talks/slides_files/libs/revealjs/plugin/notes/speaker-view/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://enjeeneer.io/talks/slides_files/libs/revealjs/plugin/notes/speaker-view/</guid>
      <description>reveal.js - Speaker View  body { font-family: Helvetica; font-size: 18px; } #current-slide, #upcoming-slide, #speaker-controls { padding: 6px; box-sizing: border-box; -moz-box-sizing: border-box; } #current-slide iframe, #upcoming-slide iframe { width: 100%; height: 100%; border: 1px solid #ddd; } #current-slide .label, #upcoming-slide .label { position: absolute; top: 10px; left: 10px; z-index: 2; } #connection-status { position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; z-index: 20; padding: 30% 20% 20% 20%; font-size: 18px; color: #222; background: #fff; text-align: center; box-sizing: border-box; line-height: 1.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://enjeeneer.io/talks/slides_files/libs/revealjs/plugin/reveal-chalkboard/readme/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://enjeeneer.io/talks/slides_files/libs/revealjs/plugin/reveal-chalkboard/readme/</guid>
      <description>Chalkboard With this plugin you can add a chalkboard to reveal.js. The plugin provides two possibilities to include handwritten notes to your presentation:
 you can make notes directly on the slides, e.g. to comment on certain aspects, you can open a chalkboard or whiteboard on which you can make notes.  The main use case in mind when implementing the plugin is classroom usage in which you may want to explain some course content and quickly need to make some notes.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
