<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>machine learning on Scott Jeen</title>
    <link>https://enjeeneer.io/tags/machine-learning/</link>
    <description>Recent content in machine learning on Scott Jeen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 15 Mar 2021 16:55:47 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://enjeeneer.io/tags/machine-learning/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Taking a peek inside black-box function approximators</title>
      <link>https://enjeeneer.io/talks/2021-03-15-xchangeseminar/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Mar 2021 16:55:47 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://enjeeneer.io/talks/2021-03-15-xchangeseminar/</guid>
      <description>Abstract
In this talk, I will introduce deterministic and probabilistic black-box function approximators, with applications for timeseries modelling. First, I introduce the multilayer perceptron (neural network), demonstrating how they can model arbitrarily complex functions, but highlighting their propensity to overfit the training data. Second, I introduce the Gaussian process (GP), a bayesian, probabilistic approach to function approximation. I visualise how GP&amp;rsquo;s quantify uncertainty, a robust trait in the context of control, but highlight their inability to scale to large datasets.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Can probabilistic machine learning help limit climate change?</title>
      <link>https://enjeeneer.io/posts/2021/01/can-probabilistic-machine-learning-help-limit-climate-change/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Jan 2021 16:33:12 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://enjeeneer.io/posts/2021/01/can-probabilistic-machine-learning-help-limit-climate-change/</guid>
      <description>🌍 If we are to successfully mitigate climate change we must reduce global emissions to near-zero by 2050. To this end, three solutions exist:
 Generate energy using emission-free technologies; Capture and bury emissions using carbon capture and storage (CCS); and Use energy more efficiently.  In the UK, emission reduction efforts via solution 1) have so far proven extremely successful. Emission-free energy technologies generated 45% of UK electricity demand in 2020 which has caused a decrease in grid carbon intensity of 66%.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
